本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
準備は進んでいるか　ナルサス
Preparations runs smoothly, Narsus?
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
すこぶる順調だ
Very smooth.
ルーシャン殿がサトライプを引き受けてくれたおかげで
As Lord Lucian took the position satraypa,
私は軍師の仕事に集中できる
I can focus on strategy.
あの老人はよくやってくれているようだな
It seems that this old man is trying to be nice.
お前などよりよほど働き者だ
Oh, he is working more than you.
Lord Ray kingdom Parsis, Lucian
What?..
なっ…　人聞きの悪いことを
Profanity nothing about me.
まるで　ふだん俺が働いていないようではないか
From your mouth it sounds like I do not work!
What's that ?!
なんだと　貴様
No-ka, repeat!
もう一度言ってみろ　シンドゥラの黒犬が
You damn black dog sindoor!
何度でも申し上げましょう
Again, as you want.
ナルサス殿の指示に従っていただきたい
I ask you to follow the instructions of Mr. Narsusa.
I saw a decree!
指示書には目を通した
But this is nonsense!
だが　なんだ　あれは
なぜ我々がダリューン殿の隊の後方支援なのだ
Why are we in the reserve group Mr. Daryuna ?!
Son of Lord Munzir of the Oxus, the kingdom of Parsa, Zaravant
You do not like something?
何か問題が
They want to push us to the rear
我らを後方に追いやって　武勲を挙げさせぬつもりか
and will not allow to prove themselves in battle ?!
Are you talking useless.
貴様では話にならぬ　ナルサス卿と話をさせろ
Let me discuss it with Mr. Narsusom!
Hey, that's enough.
おい　やめないか
先日はキシュワード殿に免じて引いてやったが
I recently stepped out of respect for Mr. Kisvardu,
commander of the garrison Zara kingdom Parsis, Tus
but this time I will not tolerate this arrogance, sindurianets!
これ以上　我らを愚弄することは許さんぞ　シンドゥラ人
いかんな　ほってはおけんか
Things are bad.
This can not be so leave.
まあまあ　皆々様
Quiet, quiet, gentlemen.
そうカリカリせず　ここはひとつ楽しく詩でもどうです
So do not be angry.
How about enjoy the song?
楽士風情が戦の話に口を挟むな
You're just a musician! Do not interfere in the conversations about the war!
Provalyvay!
引っ込んでいろ
I apologize.
これは失礼
オクサスのような片田舎の方には
I think that people from some abandoned Ochs
unlikely to be able to appreciate the beauty of music.
詩をたしなむような高尚な趣味はありませんか
貴様…
Oh you!..
ザラーヴァント殿
Mr. Dialect.
此度の編制は各部隊の特性を考慮したうえでの結果だ
We were building,
taking into account the unique characteristics of each group.
決してお主らを軽んじているわけではない
This is not an insult to your people.
But I would like to show respect for your pride and character.
だが　お主の誇りと気概は尊重したい
Allow me once again to think about it?
もう一度考えさせてもらえないだろうか
K-course. If you agree to this, Mr. Narsus.
ナルサス殿がそう言ってくれるのであれば
Jaswant, do you mind?
ジャスワントもかまわないな
I have no objections.
異存はございませぬ
行くぞ　ザラーヴァント
Idem, Zaravant.
まったく…　シンドゥラ人のみならず　旅の楽士など
That's the same ...
Not only sindurianets, but also a traveling musician ...
In my opinion, the prince in the service too suspicious persons.
えたいの知れぬ連中をそばに重用し過ぎではないのか　殿下は
口が過ぎるぞ
Do not you be the judge.
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
片源
Rei
时间轴
钦钦&雪糕
压制
Coolkid
Chapter XXI
Here's the problem.
困ったものだ
This will affect even morale troops
明日には出陣だというのに　これでは兵の士気にも関わる
and tomorrow we are going to war.
The more people, the more problems.
人が増えれば　厄介事も増えるものだ
Well, I do understand why Mr. Zaravant so unhappy.
まあ　ザラーヴァント殿が気分を害する理由も分からなくはない
彼らの立場からすれば
If you take their point of view,
確かにどこの馬の骨とも知れぬ連中に見えるだろうさ
then we look like a questionable person who undertook nowhere.
And I'm including.
私も含めてな
だが　このまま放っておくわけにもいくまい
But we can not leave all that.
Yes. It looks like we will have to make another concession.
ああ　どうやら　もう一手打つ必要があるようだな
If you cross over these mountains, then I end up in the fortress Peshavard ...
この山を越えれば　ペシャワール城塞か
Mr. Kubard, I suppose?
クバード殿とお見受けする
All clear.
なるほどな
アルスラーン王子にそちらの状況を知られては困るか
They could not explain the Prince Arslan you are coming from you?
Captain of Cavalry of the kingdom Pars, Kubard
ヒルメス王子の差し金か
You have sent Prince Hermes?
裏切り者の始末ごとき　あの方のお心を煩わせるまでもない
Rasprvlyaetes a traitor?
His Majesty should not worry about the little things!
となると　ザンデか
Mean, Zande, abuse?
すまんな　サーム
Free, Together.
As I thought. I and this people?
やはり　俺はあの連中とは　気が合いそうもない
It is unlikely that we will get along!
ありえねえな
なんだと
What?!
どうした
Oh you...
貴様…　俺の兄を射殺したというのか
That is, are you shot my brother ?!
The younger brother of the captain of cavalry from the kingdom Parsis Shapur, Esfan
A?!
だから　なんだ
So what?
I've heard stories about you.
お主のうわさは聞いているよ
Baby you abandoned on a snowy mountain
赤ん坊の頃
雪山に捨てられていたところをシャプールに助けられたんだってな
and Shapur picked up, right?
それで付けられたあだ名がファルハーディン　「狼に育てられた者」か
And then you because of this, given the nickname Farha al Din.
"Raised by wolves", huh?
My story does not play a role! And you!..
俺のことなどどうでもいい　貴様が…
I saved this guy's suffering, really.
俺はあの男を苦痛から解放してやったのだぞ
You have nothing to be angry with me.
恨まれる筋合いはないな
ギーヴ殿　言い過ぎだ
Giev lord, it is too!
I would have even been happy to hear words of gratitude.
むしろ感謝してほしいくらいなのだが
黙れ
Shut up!
やっちまえ　将軍
Show him, master!
楽士なんかに負けるな
Do not Lose some musician!
やっちまってください
やっちまえ
イスファーン　無礼な新参者に思い知らせてやれ
Esfan, to teach a lesson to this rookie-squirt!
And from my point of view
こちらにしてみれば
recruits are exactly you.
新参者はあんたらの方なのだがな
こっちは殿下がエクバターナを出たときから
Since Prince left Ecbatana,
I was always with him and protected him.
ずっとおそばでお守りしてきたんだ
今更　尻馬に乗ってきたあんたらとは違う
I'm not a sheep, which suddenly decided to join his flock like you.
Gad! Needless to listen to you!
貴様　言わせておけば…
I'll cut your tongue to keep chatting!
その長すぎる舌を適当な寸法に直してやる
Only warn
言っておくがな
From the very beginning of your brother condemned to the suffering
そもそもあんたの兄上にあのような最期を遂げさせたのは
ルシタニアの連中だぞ
Lyusitaniya itself!
だが　今　俺の前にいるのは貴様だ
But now you're in front of me!
双方　剣を引け
They set aside their swords, both of you!
王太子殿下の御前なるぞ
You are in the presence of the Crown Prince.
これは何事だ　ギーヴ　イスファーン卿
What's going on here?
Giev. Lord Esfan.
何…　人生観の相違というやつで
Well, just went to the philosophical questions.
全て見ていたぞ　ギーヴ
I saw everything, Giev!
いたずらにイスファーン殿を挑発したお前に非があるのは明白だ
You yourself started unnecessarily provoke the Lord Esfana!
だったら　どうするよ
So what?
I have long put up with your insolent behavior.
以前よりお前の勝手な行動は目に余っていた
I've had enough, that you so despise the kindness of Prince!
殿下のお優しさに甘えるのもいいかげんにしてもらおう
やれやれ
Well well.
口を開けば　「殿下　殿下」
You just keep saying: "Prince", "Prince".
And he-what? You do not patronize too?
あんたこそ　ちょっと過保護すぎやしないか
Mr Fu Mardan Mardan.
「マルダーン・フ・マルダーン」殿
そこまでだ　二人とも
Enough, you two!
Prince.
殿下
Giev.
ギーヴ
As Crown Prince Arslan
王太子アルスラーンの名の下　お主を追放する
I expel you.
よい機会だ
A great opportunity.
I thank you for everything
殿下には世話になったが
but I never wanted to serve in the palace.
もともと俺は宮仕えなど性に合わなくてな
Hey, hey, Mr. Giev!
お…おい　待て　ギーブ殿
Do not hurry!
早まるな　今すぐ殿下に…
Let the Prince knows ...
お達者で　殿下
Good day, Prince.
ご武運を祈ってますよ
I will pray for your victory.
Hey! Mr. Giev!
おい　ギーヴ殿
This was necessary Narsus?
あれで　よかったのだな…
ナルサス
It was an unpleasant role that I asked you to play ...
殿下には嫌な役回りをお願いしてしまいましたね
I'm not against.
私のことはよい
ギーヴの方にこそ　申し訳ないことをした
But with Gievom I acted unjustly.
ですが　彼が憎まれ役を引き受けてくれたことで
But he perfectly played the role of villain,
ひとまず諸侯たちの不満は抑えることができたでしょう
Now discontent of Lords for a while subside.
You do not need to worry about it, Prince.
殿下がお気に病まれることなど　何もありませぬ
Where Giev now?
それで　ギーヴは今
He had already left.
すでにたちました
彼にはとあるものを探す任務を依頼しています
I instructed him to find a single person.
Man?
とある？
That you become king,
殿下が王となられるため　いずれ必要となるかもしれないものです
we may need to help this person.
Good.
分かった　別れを言えなかったのは残念だが
Although unfortunate that I could not say goodbye to him.
あなたが王になったとき　どのような国が出来るのか
I very much want to see the kingdom that you build,
楽しみです
when you become king.
見ていてくれ　ギーヴ
Look Giev.
Forward! destroy Lyusitaniyu
行くぞ　ルシタニアを打ち倒し　王都エクバターナを取り戻す
and return the capital Ecbatana!
To battle!
出陣
Here's how.
そうか
アルスラーンめ　やはり動いたか
So Arslan made a move.
Lyusitanii king's brother, the Grand Vizier and the supreme commander of the army, Giscard
How is the mobilization?
兵の招集はどうなっている
ボードワン　モンフェラート　両将軍の働きにより
Thanks to the efforts of Baudouin and Monferrato generals
our soldiers are scattered throughout the Pars,
パルス全土に散っていた兵がエクバターナに再集結しつつあります
Now I am going to Ecbatana.
But...
しかし…
銀仮面以外は　だろう
In addition to the Silver Mask, is not it?
申し訳ありません
I apologize!
ザーブル城に送った使者はいまだ…
Messenger had not yet arrived from the castle Zabul ...
Nothing.
よい　放っておいても　ヤツは必ずここへ来るだろう
If we leave him alone, he will definitely come here.
アルスラーンの首をかき斬るためにな
To get a head Arslan.
Whatever he was up to,
ヤツの思惑がどうあれ
just going to use it as long as there is a chance.
利用できるうちは利用してやるまでだ
最後に笑うのは誰か　楽しみにしているがよい
I wonder who will have the last laugh ...
This we shall soon see.
At the moment, our goal ...
ひとまず我らが目指すのはここ　聖マヌエル城です
Here. Castle of Emmanuel.
聖マヌエル
Holy Emmanuel?
ええ　ルシタニアの歴史上の人物の名です
Yes. The name of a historical figure Lyusitanii.
This fortress past era, has long been abandoned,
古い時代の砦で　長らく放置されていたところを占拠されました
Then they occupied it.
厄介だな　この地形
There's a bad area.
ええ
Yes.
But is it right outside the continental way,
だが　大陸公路に位置するここを落とさずして　先に進むことはできません
it still can not be avoided.
城守のバルカシオンはルシタニア本国では王立図書館長を務めていた人物です
Lord of the castle guard, Barkasion,
in their homeland, Lyusitanii, served as the chief royal librarian.
Chief Librarian?
図書館長　武人ではないのですか
He was not a soldier?
This weakness we can use.
そこがつけいる隙になるだろうな
Excellent. First release this castle of St. Emmanuel,
よし　まずはこの聖マヌエル城を奪還し　王都への足掛かりとする
he supported the camp on their way to Ecbatana!
はっ
There is!
One, Mr. Narsus.
あの…　ナルサス様
If we go to the castle of St. Emmanuel here,
ここから聖マヌエル城に向かうとすると　この城の近くも通りますよね
also we are able to get close to him, right?
チャスーム城塞
Forest Chassum ...
はて　聞いたことがないが
Curious. I never heard of him ...
There has recently been settled Lyusitanii army.
ルシタニア軍が最近　新たに築城した拠点だな
公路の要点を押さえ　我らの動向を監視するのが目的だろう
Apparently, they want to control the cue point
and the way to keep track of our actions.
ギスカールとかいう男も一応　考えてはいるようだ
It seems this guy, Giscard,
also knows how to think.
Mr. Narsus!
ナルサス殿
ぜひ我らにチャスーム城攻城の許可を賜りたい
Let us pave the way to the forest Chamssum!
We will use this opportunity to show its strength prince.
我らの力を殿下にお目に掛ける機会を頂きたいのです
Your passionate outburst is not necessary.
頼もしい申し出ですが　その必要はありません
Mr. Narsus.
ナルサス殿
我々の目的は　あくまで聖マヌエル城
Our goal - only the Holy Emmanuel castle.
strategically,
戦略上　このチャスームを攻める必要はないということです
it makes no sense to take by storm Chassum.
イスファーン　ザラーヴァント　トゥース
ESF. Dialect. .
I'm flattered by your fighting spirit,
お主たちの気持ちはうれしいが
戦わずに済む戦で　大事な将兵を失いたくはない
but I do not want to lose people in a senseless battle.
ここは引いてくれぬか
You agree with that?
How view.
承知いたしました
ザラーヴァント　少し下がれ
Zaravant! Stand back!
お主こそ下がれ
depart by myself!
おい　二人とも速度を落とせ
Hey! Slow down both!
後方の部隊がついてこれんぞ
Comrades for you do not keep up!
うるさい
Shut up!
Lord.
やれやれ…
すまんが　後続の部隊は任せる
I'm sorry, but I leave with a detachment on you.
Five hundred people traveling with me!
騎兵５００ほど　ついてこい
There is!
はっ
なんだ　罠のつもりか
What? This type of trap?
あんな小細工で我らの足を止められるとは思っているのか
They think that will stop us this makeshift trap?
Wait a minute. First, to better assess the situation.
待て　一度様子を見た方がよい
You need to report to lag behind the detachment of Prince ...
後続の殿下の部隊に報告を…
こんなもん
To nothing!
Forward!
行くぞ
Hey!
お…おい
合図を
Alert!
はっ
There is!
後続が
The people behind us ...
Caught!
掛かったぞ
Do not miss the Gentiles!
異教徒どもを逃がすな
Zaravant with people ?!
ザラーヴァントたちが
完全に分断されてしまったようですね
It seems that they have finally come off.
According to the reports,
報告によれば　３隊は公路上に待ち構えていたルシタニア軍と交戦
three clashed with lyusitaniantsami, was waiting beside the road.
退路を塞がれる形で山岳地帯の方へ追いやられてしまったようです
They cut off the escape route
due to which they were driven into the mountains.
They will come back to us?
合流はできそうなのか
敵の追撃を受けているだろうし
It seems that they pursued the enemy,
間もなく日が暮れる
and the sun will soon sit.
It will be difficult to find friends on the move in the darkness.
闇の中　移動している部隊を捜すのは困難だな
Of course,
もちろん　このまま彼らを残し　進軍する
we can leave them and move on.
There is also an option, but ...
という選択肢もありますが
There's nothing to think about.
迷うことではない
Stop the entire army and prepare a rescue team.
全軍の進軍を止め　救出部隊の準備を
I have already sent Elam and the Alfred exploration.
すでにエラムとアルフリードに偵察に出てもらっています
As soon as they return, go for help.
彼らが戻りしだい　救出に向かいましょう
頼む
You are welcome.
I too longed to excel ...
功を焦り過ぎたか…
only themselves to blame, and therefore I can.
自業自得ということか
見つからなかったか
So you have not found them.
申し訳ありません
I'm sorry.
この辺りは切り立った岩山が迷路のように入り組んでいて
On the territory is full of steep cliffs that form a labyrinth ...
That night and the moon is not.
今夜は月も出ないし
Sadly, we are powerless.
残念だけど　これ以上は無理よ
ラジェンドラのときとは逆に　地の利を敵に取られた格好ですね
It's not the way in the battle against Rajendra.
Now we have a situation where the enemy territorial advantage.
何か手はないのか
And we can not do anything?
This sound ...
この音は
Quiet! Guys, silence!
待て　皆　静かにしてくれ
どうやら　物好きなジンが彼らの居場所を教えてくれているようですな
It seems capricious jin tell us where they are.
ああ
Yes!
It looks like we're surrounded.
囲まれたようだな
I did such a way to be on the side of Prince Arslan ...
せっかく殿下のもとにはせ参じたというのに
なんの武勲も挙げられぬまま　こんな所で
And I do not even get a chance to prove themselves in battle ...
There is nothing to be upset.
そう嘆くな
我らがここで犠牲になればこそ
That's our victim here and now
殿下の本隊は無傷で先に進めるというものだ
It allows to pass the main army of Prince unharmed.
If you think so,
そう考えれば　決して無駄死にではないか
then our death will not be in vain.
いつの間に
When they have time? ..
どうなってる
What's happening?!
There our people! Forward!
味方だ　行くぞ
Yes! For mnoy!
続け
We are saved ...
助かったのか
ザラーヴァント　イスファーン　トゥース
Dialect! ESF! This!
殿下
Prince.
三人とも無事でよかった
I am glad that you are safe.
With all due respect...
恐れながら…
Why did you come back?
なぜ戻ってこられたのですか
我々を捨て駒にして　そのまま先に進んでしまえばよかったものを
You could just donate us as pawns, and go further ...
確かに　そうすれば　今は楽でしたが
Yes,
so it would be easier.
だが　この先のことを考えれば
But, considering what lies ahead,
お主たちをここで失うわけにはいかない
we can not afford to lose people.
聞いてくれ
Listen.
国を取り戻すためのこれからの戦い　多くの犠牲が必要だろう
In the battle for the return of our country
it takes a lot of victims.
But
だが　それでも私は少しでも多くの者に生きてほしい
I still want to survive as many people as possible.
どうか　お主たちの力を生きるために貸してくれまいか
You lend me your strength to stay alive?
Prince...
殿下…
Prince.
殿下
The three of us again ask you to allow you to serve.
我ら三人　改めてあなたに忠誠を誓わせていただきます
Go, so nothing to say?
何も言わずに行くつもりか
宮仕えが性に合わんってのは本当だからな
When I said that's not my style to serve in the palace, it was true.
しばらく戻るつもりはない
I will not be for some time.
ナルサスからの依頼もあるしな
I have a job because of Narsusa.
Clear.
そうか　なら止めはすまい
Then I will not stop.
だが一つだけ　殿下から伝言だ　聞いていけ
I can only say one thing.
Message from the prince. Listen.
He said: "I regret what gives you problems until the very end."
最後まで面倒をかけてすまない…　と
To live, to go on a trip ...
生きることは旅だつこと　死もまた同じ
So, to be in the hands of death.
時の河をわたる鳥の翼は
Wing of a bird, flew the river of time,
It brings old age man only one stroke.
ひとはばたきに人を老いさせる…
At night, when you miss me
俺がいなくて寂しい夜は
この詩を思い出してくれよ
remember this song.
覚えておこう
I'll remember it.
Although it did not work out very well composed Rubaie.
Note .: Rubaiyat - quatrain; a form of lyric poetry, is widespread in the Middle East
あまり出来のよろしくないルバイヤートじゃがな
じゃあな
To.
YakuSub Studio
kimi ga deatta kokoro wa kitto
All the souls that you could meet on the way,
translation Mu_Cool
hitotsu datte machigai janai
certainly it was pure and innocent,
Editorial Mu_Cool
onaji yume wo daite
We kept the same dream.
Making Weekend
michi wo tagaeta hito wo omotta
People walking different paths,
nozarashi no akogare wo kakagete susumu kouya
killed all my hopes and desires revive again.
hohoemi mo sono namida mo
Smile on his face, tears running down her cheeks,
koko ni suteteyukenai kara
If you want to go ahead, they should not be forgotten.
kage wo daite shiroku takaku
Covered by the shadow of the summer, so white and immense,
namonaki boku to kimi no hata
our with you nameless flag flies.
mada hatenaku tsudzuku kono mich ino kanata ni
There, on the road, which extends an endless path,
tatta hitotsu no hikari wo sen no kokoro ni
There is one bright light, and with it a thousand souls.
miageru sora wo shinjiteru
Believe in the sky above his head,
michibiku hoshi wo higashi no takami ni sashishimesu yo
there putevodnaâ our star in the east, ee do not engage.
yume wa kono te de kanaeru
And their cherished dream in flesh forces.
Zabul Castle
魔道の者よりの報告では
According to the report of one of the wizards
出陣したアルスラーン軍はチャスーム城塞を抜け
Arslan has nominated Army
held forest Chassum
そのまま西へ進軍を続けているようです
and continues to move to the west.
そうか
Clear.
And we are advancing.
我らも出る　準備を急げ
Quickly prepare everything.
はっ
There is.
Well, go on, Arslan.
さあ　来い　アルスラーン
待っているぞ
I'm waiting for you.
We will solve all our questions at the appropriate stage for us.
貴様との決着にふさわしい舞台を用意してな
あし毛の馬に揺られるアルスラーンは出撃以来　無口であった
Swaying in the saddle, his gray dappled horse
Arslan sits in silence from the beginning of the battle.
考えねばならないことが　いくつもあった
In his head swarming countless thoughts.
次回　出撃前夜
Next time:. "The night before the attack"
Chapter XXII
少年は　そして王となる
And so the guy would be King.